A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Oral History Project FA618
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Oral History Project
1965-2006
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA618
14.8 Cubic Feet Extent is approximate.
Biographical / Historical
In 1970 the Executive Committee of the Board of Trustees of the Ford Foundation approved a project to record oral history interviews with past and present trustees, officers and staff members. The project was designed to gather material for future historical analysis of the organization of the Foundation and the evolution of its program. On June 10, 1971, Foundation President McGeorge Bundy approved President’s Authority Project #07190398 for $232,800 to finance the work. Charles T. Morrissey, Director of the Vermont Historical Society and President of the Oral History Association, was named Project Director. Ronald J. Grele, who had worked on the John F. Kennedy Library oral history project, was named Assistant Director. From 1971-1974 over 70 persons were interviewed by Morrissey and Grele. The audio recordings were transcribed and indexed during 1973-1974, with additional funding provided by a supplement to the original grant.
Scope and Contents
Oral History Project records include administrative correspondence and memoranda, background materials and interview notes compiled by project staff, audio recordings and transcripts of interviews and a name/subject index. Documentation concerning the origins and administration of the project dates from 1965-2006. Subjects discussed in the interviews themselves include the role of the Ford family in establishing the Foundation, the preparation of the Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program, program development and operations, staffing, administration and the involvement of Trustees in Foundation affairs.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series and subseries:
I. Administrative Files; II. Audio Recordings; III. Index; IV. Transcripts
Related Materials
A substantial oral history of former Ford Foundation India Representative Douglas Ensminger was recorded during 1971-1973, but was not formally a part of the project covered by these records. The Ensminger oral history and related materials are also held by the Ford Foundation Archives and are available separately.
Former Foundation Vice President F. Champion Ward composed a memoir of his experiences as a consultant and officer of the Foundation in 1985, in lieu of an oral history interview. The Ward memoir is held by the Archives and is available as Report #012126.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Audio recordings (Series II) are restricted from scholary research.
Access to some interviews is limited or restricted based on observance of the stipulations established by interviewees in their respective oral history agreements. Interviews are open to scholarly research as applicable restrictions expire. Consult Archivist for further information.
Index is closed to scholarly research.
Oral histories; Oral history; Ford Foundation
- Administrative Files, 1965-2005; I; 2.4 Cubic Feet 2 record storage cartons.
  - Access policies and procedures, 1973-2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Possible additional interviews, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes correspondence between James Armsey, Richard Magat, Alan Divack, Michael Lipsky, and Susan Berresford, discussing the addition of oral history interviews to the Foundation’s archive. No additional oral history interviews were made at the time.
  - Nonparticipants
    Includes oral history candidates who did not participate, and interviewees who withdrew from the project.
    - Abrams, Frank, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Armsey, James W., 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Benton, William, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bechtel, Stephen D., 1973 (Box 3 (AV))
      Audio tape memoranda
    - Cole, Fred (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Cowles, John, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Ensminger, Douglas, 1973-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Friendly, Fred W., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Hoffman, Paul G., 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Sutton, Francis X., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Ward, F. Champion, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Interviewees
    - Bell, David E., 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Berelson, Bernard, 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Bixler, Paul H., 1972-2005 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Black, Eugene, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Borgmann, Carl W., 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Brown, Dyke, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Bundy, McGeorge, 1973-2000 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Coombs, Philip H., 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - David, Donald K., 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Davis, Chester, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Donaldson, William H., 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Dressner, Howard R., 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Ellis, James R., 1972-1985 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Ethridge, Mark F., 1972-1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Eurich, Alvin C., 1974-1987 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Faust, Clarence, 1972-1985 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Ferry, W. H., 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Fletcher, C. Scott, 1972-2005 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Ford, Benson, 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Ford, Henry II, 1972-1985 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Fox, Melvin J., 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Gladieux, Bernard L., 1972-1985 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Gordon, Kermit, 1972-1977 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Gould. Laurence M., 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Griffiths, George H., 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Gustavson, Reuben G., 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Haas, Walter A., 1972-1997 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Harkavy, Oscar, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Harrison, Gordon, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Heald, Henry T., 1971-1985 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Heard, Alexander, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Henderson, Vivian, 1972-1982 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Hertz, Willard J., 1974 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Hill, F.F., 1972-1984 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Howard, John B., 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Hutchins, Robert M., 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Katz, Milton, 1972-1979 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Kennan, George F., 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Land, Edwin H., 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Larsen, Roy E., 1971-1979 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Laughlin, James, 1972-1979 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Loudon, John H., 1974 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Lowry, W. McNeil, 1971-1981 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - McCloy, John J., 1972-1984 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - McDaniel, Joseph M., 1971-1976 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - McKeever, Porter, 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - McNamara, Robert S., 1974 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - McNeely, Janet, 1974-2006 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Magat, Richard, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Marquis, Donald G., 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Marshall, Dorothy N., 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Miller, J. Irwin, 1974-1984 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Morrill, James L., 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Nielsen, Waldemar, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Nims, William H., 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Plante, Lilian, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Price, Don K., 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Saudek, Robert, 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Sheldon, Richard C., 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Slater, Joseph E., 1972-1984 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Spaeth, Carl, 1972-1977 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Stone, Shepard, 1972-1984 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Stratton, Julius A., 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Sviridoff, Mitchell, 1974-1985 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Thompson, Marcia, 1973-1976 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Wald, Patricia M., 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Webster, Bethuel M., 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Wright, Thomas H., 1974 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Wyzanski, Charles E., 1968-1984 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Ylvisaker, Paul N., 1972-1979 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Young, James Webb, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Project origins, 1965-1974 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Restriction schedules, 1974-2005 (Box 4, Folder 85)
- Index, III; 17 Box(es) 3.5x5x12 inches each
  - A - Behavioral Science (Box 5)
  - Behavioral Science - BY (Box 6)
  - C - Cox (Box 7)
  - Cox Committee - Ensemble Theater (Box 8)
  - Ensminger - Ford Foundation (Box 9)
  - Ford Foundation - Ford Foundation officers (Box 10)
  - Ford Foundation offices - Foundations (Box 11)
  - Four Continents - Gottbaum (Box 12)
  - Gould - Hoffman (Box 13)
  - Hoffman - India (Box 14)
  - India program - Lowrie (Box 15)
  - Lowry - Monson (Box 16)
  - Morrill - Peace Corps (Box 17)
  - Pearson - Rockefeller (Box 18)
  - Rockefeller - Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (Box 19)
  - Study for the Ford Foundation... - Ward (Box 20)
  - Ward - Z (Box 21)
- Transcripts, IV; 8 Cubic Feet
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access to some interviews is limited or restricted based on observance of the stipulations established by interviewees in their respective oral history agreements. Interviews are opened to research as applicable restrictions expire. Consult Archivist for further information.
  - Master copies, 4.4 Cubic Feet 10 standard document boxes.
    All master copies are restricted from scholarly access.
    - Bell, David, 1972 November 16, December 15 (Box 22, Folder 86)
    - Berelson, Bernard, 1972 July 7 (Box 22, Folder 87)
    - Bixler, Paul H., 1972 November 1 (Box 22, Folder 88)
    - Black, Eugene, 1972 August 1 (Box 22, Folder 89)
    - Borgmann, Carl W., 1973 January 22 (Box 22, Folder 90)
    - Brown, Dyke, 1972-1973; 199 pages. (Box 22, Folder 91)
    - Bundy, McGeorge, 1972 February 11
      Missing / Not housed at RAC.
    - Coombs, Philip H., 1973 July 10 (Box 23, Folder 92)
    - David, Donald K., 1972 March 14, 23 (Box 23, Folder 93)
    - Davis, Chester, 1972 April 21 (Box 23, Folder 94)
    - Donaldson, William H.
    - Dressner, Howard R.
    - Ellis, James R., 1973 July 20 (Box 23, Folder 95)
    - Ethridge, Mark F., 1972 May 8 (Box 23, Folder 96)
    - Eurich, Alvin C., 1972 November 28 (Box 23, Folder 97)
    - Faust, Clarence, 1972 January 30; 1973 January 31, February 1 (Box 23, Folder 98)
    - Ferry, W.H., 1972 July 13, 25 (Box 24, Folder 99)
    - Fletcher, C. Scott, 1973 March 1, 2, 3 (Box 24, Folder 100)
    - Ford, Benson, 1973 May 24 (Box 24, Folder 101)
    - Ford, Henry II, 1973 August 1 (Box 24, Folder 102)
    - Fox, Melvin J., 1972 October 24, 27, November 2, 8, 21, December 5 (Box 24, Folder 103)
    - Gladieux, Bernard L., 1972 June 29 (Box 24, Folder 104)
    - Gordon, Kermit, 1972 December 19 (Box 25, Folder 105)
    - Gould, Laurence M., 1973 January 25, 26 (Box 25, Folder 106)
    - Griffiths, George H., 1972 September 20
    - Gustavson, Reuben G., 1973 January 25 (Box 25, Folder 107)
    - Haas, Walter A., 1973 July 18 (Box 25, Folder 108)
    - Harkavy, Oscar
    - Harrison, Gordon, 1972 November 21, 30, December 22 (Box 25, Folder 109)
    - Heald, Henry T., 1972 January 7, February 24, 25 (Box 25, Folder 110)
    - Heard, Alexander, 1972 December 21; 1974 September 24 (Box 25, Folder 111)
    - Henderson, Vivian, 1973 April 16 (Box 25, Folder 112)
    - Hertz, Willard, 1973 May 8; 1974 December 23 (Box 26, Folder 113)
    - Hill, F.F., 1973 April 20 (Box 26, Folder 114)
    - Howard, John B., 1973 February 13, 15, 23 (Box 26, Folder 115)
    - Hutchins, Robert M., 1972 May 23, 24 (Box 26, Folder 116)
    - Katz, Milton, 1972 June 22 (Box 26, Folder 117)
    - Kennan, George F., 1972 March 29 (Box 26, Folder 118)
    - Land, Edwin H., 1973 August 20 (Box 27, Folder 119)
    - Larsen, Roy E., 1972 October 25 (Box 27, Folder 120)
    - Laughlin, James
    - Loudon, John H., 1972 December 7 (Box 27, Folder 121)
    - Lowry, W. McNeil, 1972 January 14, 18, 26, December 4, 11, 18; 1973 February 12, 26, March 6, April 24, May 7, 17, 30, August 27, November 16; 1974 April 23 (Box 27, Folder 122-123)
    - McCloy, John J., 1972 June 26, July 26 (Box 28, Folder 124)
    - McDaniel, Joseph M., 1971 November 17, December 1, 2, 9; 1972 January 5, 13, 19, February 2, 9, 16, July 25, August 3 (Box 28, Folder 125-126)
    - McKeever, Porter, 1973 August 15 (Box 28, Folder 127)
    - McNamara, Robert S., 1972 December 6 (Box 28, Folder 128)
    - McNeely, Janet, 1973 November 27; 68 pages. (Box 28, Folder 129)
    - Magat, Richard, 1974 January 24, March 14 (Box 29, Folder 130)
    - Marquis, Donald G., 1972 October 27 (Box 29, Folder 131)
    - Marshall, Dorothy N., 1973 August 21 (Box 29, Folder 132)
    - Miller, J. Irwin
    - Morrill, James L., 1972 November 2 (Box 29, Folder 133)
    - Nielsen, Waldemar, 1972 November 2 (Box 29, Folder 134)
    - Nims, William H., 1971 November 5 (Box 29, Folder 135)
    - Plante, Lilian, 1972 June 14; 1974 April 2 (Box 29, Folder 136)
    - Price, Don K., 1972 June 22-23 (Box 29, Folder 137)
    - Saudek, Robert
    - Sheldon, Richard C., 1973 August 7 (Box 30, Folder 138)
    - Slater, Joseph E., 1973 February 2 (Box 30, Folder 139)
    - Spaeth, Carl, 1972 April 24 (Box 30, Folder 140)
    - Stone, Shepard, 1972 December 12; 55 pages. (Box 30, Folder 141)
    - Stratton, Julius A., 1972 February 18, October 18 (Box 30, Folder 142)
    - Sviridoff, Mitchell, 1974 February 12, March 4; 73 pages. (Box 30, Folder 143)
    - Thompson, Marcia, 1974 August 16 (Box 30, Folder 144)
    - Wald, Patricia M., 1972 December 19 (Box 30, Folder 145)
    - Webster, Bethuel M., 1972 June 9 (Box 31, Folder 146)
    - Wright, Thomas H., Jr., 1973 July 19 (Box 31, Folder 147)
      Includes correspondence and memos related to Wright's oral history interview.
    - Wyzanski, Charles E., 1972 June 5, 21 (Box 31, Folder 148)
    - Ylvisaker, Paul N., 1973 September 27, October 27 (Box 31, Folder 149)
    - Young, James Webb, 1973 January 24 (Box 31, Folder 150)
  - Access copies, 3.6 Cubic Feet 3 record storage cartons
    - Bell, David, 1972 November 16, December 15; 113 pages. (Box 32, Folder 151)
    - Berelson, Bernard, 1972 July 7; 111 pages. (Box 32, Folder 152-153)
    - Bixler, Paul H., 1972 November 1; 40 pages. (Box 32, Folder 154-155)
    - Black, Eugene, 1972 August 1; 35 pages. (Box 32, Folder 156)
    - Borgmann, Carl W., 1973 January 22; 94 pages. (Box 32, Folder 157)
    - Brown, Dyke, 1972-1973 (Box 32, Folder 158)
    - Bundy, McGeorge, 1972 February 11; 55 pages. (Box 33, Folder 159)
    - Coombs, Philip H., 1973 July 10; 121 pages. (Box 33, Folder 160)
    - David, Donald K., 1972 March 14, 23; 59 pages. (Box 33, Folder 160)
    - Davis, Chester, 1972 April 21; 39 pages. (Box 33, Folder 162)
    - Donaldson, William H.
    - Dressner, Howard R.
    - Ellis, James R., 1973 July 20; 54 pages. (Box 33, Folder 163)
    - Ethridge, Mark F., 1972 May 8; 48 pages. (Box 33, Folder 164)
    - Eurich, Alvin C., 1972 November 28; 92 pages. (Box 33, Folder 165)
    - Faust, Clarence, 1972 January 30; 1973 January 31, February 1; 202 pages. (Box 33, Folder 166)
    - Ferry, W.H., 1972 July 13, 25; 111 pages. (Box 33, Folder 167)
    - Fletcher, C. Scott, 1973 March 1, 2, 3; 201 pages. (Box 34, Folder 168)
    - Ford, Benson, 1973 May 24; 55 pages. (Box 34, Folder 169)
    - Ford, Henry II, 1973 August 1; 65 pages. (Box 34, Folder 170)
    - Fox, Melvin J., 1972 October 24, 27, November 2, 8, 21, December 5; 261 pages. (Box 34, Folder 171-172)
    - Gladieux, Bernard L., 1972 June 29; 54 pages. (Box 34, Folder 173)
    - Gordon, Kermit, 1972 December 19; 59 pages. (Box 34, Folder 174)
    - Gould, Laurence M., 1973 January 25, 26; 79 pages. (Box 34, Folder 175)
    - Griffiths, George H., 1972 September 20; 58 pages. (Box 34, Folder 176)
    - Gustavson, Reuben G., 1973 January 25; 18 pages. (Box 35, Folder 177)
    - Haas, Walter A., 1973 July 18; 29 pages. (Box 35, Folder 178)
    - Harkavy, Oscar
    - Harrison, Gordon, 1972 November 21, 30, December 22; 88 pages. (Box 35, Folder 179)
    - Heald, Henry T., 1972 January 7, February 24, 25; 119 pages. (Box 35, Folder 180)
    - Heard, Alexander, 1972 December 21; 1974 September 24; 88 pages. (Box 35, Folder 181)
    - Henderson, Vivian, 1973 April 16; 52 pages. (Box 35, Folder 182)
    - Hertz, Willard, 1973 May 8; 1974 December 23; 249 pages (2 folders). (Box 35, Folder 183-184)
    - Hill, F.F., 1973 April 20; 98 pages. (Box 35, Folder 185)
    - Howard, John B., 1973 February 13, 15, 23; 166 pages. (Box 36, Folder 186)
    - Hutchins, Robert M., 1972 May 23, 24; 54 pages. (Box 36, Folder 187)
    - Katz, Milton, 1972 June 22; 70 pages. (Box 36, Folder 188)
    - Kennan, George F., 1972 March 29; 35 pages. (Box 36, Folder 189)
    - Land, Edwin H., 1973 August 20; 18 pages. (Box 36, Folder 190)
    - Larsen, Roy E., 1972 October 25; 31 pages. (Box 36, Folder 191)
    - Laughlin, James, 1973 May 22; 62 pages. (Box 36, Folder 192)
    - Loudon, John H., 1972 December 7; 47 pages. (Box 36, Folder 193)
    - Lowry, W. McNeil, 1972 January 14, 18, 26, December 4, 11, 18; 1973 February 12, 26, March 6, April 24, May 7, 17, 30, August 27, November 16; 1974 April 23; 604 pages (3 folders). (Box 36-37, Folder 194-197)
    - McCloy, John J., 1972 June 26, July 26; 34 pages. (Box 37, Folder 198)
    - McDaniel, Joseph M., 1971 November 17, December 1, 2, 9; 1972 January 5, 13, 19, February 2, 9, 16, July 25, August 3; 499 pages (4 folders). (Box 37, Folder 199-202)
    - McKeever, Porter, 1973 August 15; 51 pages. (Box 38, Folder 203)
    - McNamara, Robert S., 1972 December 6; 24 pages. (Box 38, Folder 204)
    - McNeely, Janet, 1973 November 27 (Box 38, Folder 205)
    - Magat, Richard, 1974 January 24, March 14; 111 pages. (Box 38, Folder 206)
    - Marquis, Donald G., 1972 October 27; 42 pages. (Box 38, Folder 207)
    - Marshall, Dorothy N., 1973 August 21; 28 pages. (Box 38, Folder 208)
    - Miller, J. Irwin
    - Morrill, James L., 1972 November 2; 40 pages. (Box 38, Folder 209)
    - Nielsen, Waldemar, 1972 October 5; 46 pages. (Box 38, Folder 210)
    - Nims, William H., 1971 November 5; 23 pages. (Box 38, Folder 211)
    - Plante, Lilian, 1972 June 14; 1974 April 2; 102 pages. (Box 38, Folder 212)
    - Price, Don K., 1972 June 22, 23; 110 pages. (Box 38, Folder 213)
    - Saudek, Robert, 1972 September 14; 48 pages. (Box 38, Folder 214)
    - Sheldon, Richard C., 1973 August 7; 139 pages. (Box 39, Folder 215)
    - Slater, Joseph E., 1973 February 2; 77 pages. (Box 39, Folder 216)
    - Spaeth, Carl, 1972 April 24; 69 pages. (Box 39, Folder 217)
    - Stone, Shepard, 1972 December 12; 55 pages. (Box 39, Folder 218)
    - Stratton, Julius A., 1972 February 18, October 18; 106 pages. (Box 39, Folder 219)
    - Sviridoff, Mitchell, 1974 February 12, March 4; 73 pages. (Box 39, Folder 220)
    - Thompson, Marcia, 1974 August 16; 33 pages. (Box 39, Folder 221)
    - Wald, Patricia M., 1972 December 19; 36 (Box 39, Folder 222)
    - Ward, F. Champion, 1985; 157 pages. (Box 39, Folder 223)
      Existence and Location of Copies
      A copy of Ward's memoir is filed in the Unpublished Reports, as Report #012126.
    - Webster, Bethuel M., 1972 June 9; 33 pages. (Box 39, Folder 224)
    - Wright, Thomas H., Jr., 1973 July 19; 76 pages. (Box 40, Folder 225)
    - Wyzanski, Charles E., 1972 June 5, 21; 184 pages. (Box 40, Folder 226)
    - Ylvisaker, Paul N., 1973 September 27, October 27; 81 pages. (Box 40, Folder 227)
    - Young, James Webb, 1973 January 24; 28 pages. (Box 40, Folder 228)